Guide to the Brocklehurst Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Brocklehurst family papers
1871-1945
MS 1569
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
The papers consist of correspondence, estate papers, maps and other materials which document the purchase and management of the Vergelegen estate near the Lydenburg goldfields, Northern Transvaal, by the Brocklehurst family. Charles Brocklehurst had purchased Vergelegen in 1882, amidst rumors of gold and silver discoveries. The papers provide evidence of "gold fever" in the Transvaal, as well as, surveying practices, land transactions, and estate management in the Transvaal in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. Papers documenting the activities of the Transvaal Land Owners' Association, of which E. H. Brocklehurst was a member, and the acquisition of the Kameelfontein estate in the Nylstroom district of the South African Republic are also included.
Brocklehurst family
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred from the African Collection Curator, 1998.
Arrangement
Arranged in two series: I: Kameelfontein and Vergelegen Estates, 1871-1943, n.d. II: Transvaal Land Owners' Association, 1905-1945.
Scope and Contents
The Brocklehurst Family papers consist of correspondence, maps and plans, title deeds, and an extensive collection of other estate documents which record the purchase, management and sale of the Kameelfontein and Vergelegen estates by the Brocklehurst family from 1871 to 1945. This comprehensive corpus of material will be relevant to those seeking information and insight into the various aspects of land ownership in the Transvaal during the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. From the large collection of letters and estate documents, such as power of attorney papers, title deeds, inspection reports, and land survey papers, to the small selection of maps and plans, newspapers and photographs, the researcher will find detailed information about surveying practices and procedures, land transactions, and estate management in the Transvaal during the span of approximately seventy four years. Furthermore, the papers provide evidence of the vastness of "gold fever" in the Transvaal during the latter part of the nineteenth century.
The large collection of Transvaal Land Owners' Association papers include a variety of business documents that provide further information about the transactions associated with acquiring and managing property in the Transvaal. The papers, which date from 1905 to 1945, include business correspondence, rent statements, memoranda, quarterly reports, and newspaper clippings. These documents not only illustrate the scope of the responsibilities that come with owning estate property, but also communicate the purpose and importance of this type of association during the time.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Limpopo (South Africa); Brocklehurst family; Vergelegen Farm (Cape of Good Hope)
- Kameelfontein and Vergelegen Estates, 1871-1943; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically by material type. It is comprised of materials relating to both the Kameelfontein and Vergelegen estates that document their purchase, management and eventual sale. Also included are descriptions of the physical geography of the two estates. Materials in the General folder are arranged chronologically, and include power of attorney documents, miscellaneous letters, land survey papers, inspection reports, and newspaper clippings. Correspondence is divided into two subgroups, Alphabetical and Topical. Alphabetical correspondence is comprised of outgoing letters arranged by the sender's last name. Topical correspondence is arranged alphabetically by subject matter, and contain numerous letters which document specific events and transactions that occurred in relation to the properties. In addition, there is a small collection of maps and plans, copies of the contemporary newspaper, Staats-Courant, two original photographs of the Pilgrim's Rest goldfields, and several original and translated title deeds.
  - General, 1882-1943, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-9)
  - Correspondence
    - Alphabetical
      - Brocklehurst, Frank, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Brocklehurst, General J. F., 1890-1900 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Caine, John, 1885-1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Derby, Lord, 1884 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Gill, Professor James, 1881-1887 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
      - Simpson Schappert, 1884-1894 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Townroe, R. T., 1882-1883 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Webster, Captain, 1881-1884 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Topical
      - Illovo township plots, 1909-1926 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Jane Furse Memorial Hospital, 1919-1928 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Mineral assay, 1906-1908 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Pasturage agreement, 1885-1893 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Payment dispute, 1884-1885 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Sale of Vergelegen to local natives, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Maps, 1883-1884 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newspapers, 1884-1925 (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Title deeds, 1871-1882 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- Transvaal Land Owners' Association, 1905-1945; Series II
  The Transvaal Land Owners' Association materials are arranged in chronological order, and record the functions and activities of the association during the time in which E. H. Brocklehurst was a member. Documents in the series include business correspondence, rent statements, newspaper clippings, memoranda, membership renewal notices, quarterly reports, land revenue receipts and association meeting notices.
  - Transvaal Land Owners' Association
    - 1905-1910 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1912-1917 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1918 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1919 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1920 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1921 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1922 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1923 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - 1924 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - 1925 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - 1926 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1927 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - 1928 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 1929 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - 1930 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - 1931 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - 1932 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1933 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - 1934 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - 1935 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - 1936 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1937 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - 1938 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - 1939 (Box 7, Folder 24)
    - 1940 (Box 7, Folder 25)
    - 1941 (Box 7, Folder 26)
    - 1942 (Box 7, Folder 27)
    - 1943-1944 (Box 7, Folder 28)
    - 1945 (Box 7, Folder 29)